Today we're going to talk
about the four fundamental
building blocks from which all
Android applications are built.
These building blocks
are implemented as Java classes.
And the first of these building blocks,
is the activity class.
Now, that's the main class that users
see when they run an application.
Activities are designed to provide
a graphical user interface, or
a gui, to the user.
And this enables users to give and receive
information to and from an application.
The remaining three components
work behind the scenes, so
they don't have user interfaces.
And these components include services for
supporting long-running or
in the background operations.
Broadcast receivers that listen for and
respond to events that happen on a device.
And content providers which allow multiple
applications to store and share data.
Applications are typically created from
multiple collaborating components.
Which Android starts up and
runs as necessary.
And each of these components
serves a different purpose in
the Android ecosystem.
And therefore has its own entry point and
its own APIs.
Let's take a look at each of
these components one at a time.
First, let's talk about
the activity class.
As I said earlier,
this class is designed to present
a graphical user interface to the user.
And to capture the user's
interaction through that interface.
As a general rule of thumb,
an activity should support a single
focused thing that the user can do.
A single thing like
dialing a phone number, or
entering contact information for
a single person and so on.
Now, of course as device screens,
especially those on tablets,
get larger and larger, what we mean
by a single focused thing that
the user can do is of
course bound to change.
Now as an example of an activity,
let's take a look at
the phone dialer application.
Here, I'll show you the phone
application running on an actual device.
You remember from earlier lessons
that the phone application can open
a user interface with multiple tabs.
One for a phone dialer, one for
the call log, and one for a contact list.
On Android 4.2,
this application source code is actually
part of the context application.
And it's written in a file
called Dial tacksActivity.java.
Here, I'll open that file.
As you can see, the Dial tacksActivity
class is a subclass of activity.
And the comments here,
explain that this activity is supposed to
display a tab containing the phone,
the phone dialer, the call log.
And the contacts list
that I mentioned earlier.
Let me pause here, and give you a chance
to explore this source code for yourself.
The next component is the service class.
Unlike activities,
services run in the background.
So there's no need for
services to have user interfaces.
Instead services have two main purposes,
one they can
perform long running operations
typically away from the main UI thread.
And two, they provide a way for
different processes to request
operations and share data.
Now for an example of a service, let's
take a look at the music application.
So here I'll show you the music
application running on a device.
As you can see, the music application
has a number of different user
interface screens.
That show for example your music.
Showing the songs performed
by a single artist.
Letting you select one
song by that artist.
And finally letting you
play that one song.
Now if you start playing the song,
however, and then decide to back up and
see what other songs that artist has.
Or if you want to do something totally
different, like check your email.
You probably don't want
the music to stop playing.
So Android handles this by using
a service to play the music.
Now here I'll go to
the music application and
open the MediaPlaybackservice.java file.
As you can see, the MediaPlayback
service is a subclass of service.
And the comments explain that this
service allows the music to keep playing,
even if the user switches
between different activities.
Again, let me pause here and
give you a chance to explore
this source code for yourself.
The next component is BroadcastReceiver.
BroadcastReceivers listen for
and respond to events.
And essentially they play the role
of the subscriber in the publish
subscribe pattern.
In Android, events are represented
by the intent class which we'll
talk about more in later classes.
Publishers create these intents and
then broadcast them using a method like
the context classes send broadcast.
Now once broadcasts these intents are then
routed to the broadcast receivers that
have subscribed to or registered for
those specific intents.
At which point they can
respond to the event.
Now the messaging application is one
example application that makes use of
broadcast receivers.
Let's take a look at that application.
So let's imagine that somewhere
out there in the world,
someone decides that they want
to sent me an SMS message.
That SMS message will be created, and
sent, and
will flow through the telephone network.
And eventually arrive at my phone.
And when it does, Android will put a
notification icon in the notification bar
to let me know that an SMS
message has arrived for me.
Now, of course, you can't know exactly
when you're going to receive such
a message.
So Android has some software that just
sits and waits for SMS messages to arrive.
And when they do, that software
broadcasts an, SMS_received, intent.
And there is another broadcast receiver
that is listening for that intent.
And that broadcast receiver will
eventually receive the intent and will
then start up a service that will download
and store the incoming SMS message.
Now here I'll go to
the MMS application and
open one of its broadcast receivers,
SMSReceiver.Java.
As you can see, the SMSReceiver class
is a sub class of broadcast receiver.
And the comments explain that
this broadcast receiver hands off
the incoming SMS message to a service
which take cares of the downloading and
storage of the message.
Now once more, let's pause here and
explore the source,
the source code for yourself.
The last component is content provider.
Content provider allows applications
to store and share data.
Content providers use
a database style interface.
But they're more than just databases.
For example, content providers will
handle the low level details of
interprocess communication.
So that applications running in
separate processes can communicate and
exchange data safely and easily.
The browser application is one
example of an application that uses
content providers.
So here,
I'll start the browser application.
If I click on the icon
next to the address bar,
the browser opens a list of bookmarks or
saved addresses for
websites that I might want to
access quickly in the future.
When a user adds one of these bookmarks
the browser application stores it
in a content provider.
Let's open the browser
application sourcecode and
take a look at
the BrowserProvider.java file.
As you can see, the browser provider
is a sub class of content provider.
And if we nose around
a bit in the sourcecode,
you can see some suggestions that there's
a database table called bookmarks.
Which is used for
storing the bookmarks that the user adds.
I'll pause again here and let you
explore this source code for yourself.
In our last class we looked at
the Hello Android application.
That simple application involved
just a single activity.
Today however, we're going to look
at a more complex application,
in this case comprised of two activities.
And of course once you know how to use
two activities, adding a third and
a fourth and so
on would just be more of the same.
This application is called map location,
and
one of its activities allows
the user to enter a postal address.
That activity also provides a button
that the user can press once he or
she has entered that address.
And pressing that button will then start
up a second activity, Google Maps,
that presents a map centered on
the address that the user just entered.
Let's take a look.
Now this graphic depicts the process of
writing and building Android applications.
First you create the source code and
the non-source code resources
that make up your application.
Next, tools compiles your source code and
prepare your resources.
The output of this step
is an Android package, or
APK, which corresponds to your
application's executable.
Next, the APK is digitally signed
to identify you as its developer.
And finally the APK is installed
on a device or emulator and run.
As a developer, your participation
in the build process will
usually involve the following four steps.
Defining resources,
implementing the application classes,
packaging the application and
installing and running the application.
In particular for testing and debugging.
Step one is defining your
application's resources.
As I've said before, Android applications
are more than just source code.
They include non-source
code entities as well.
Things like layout files, strings,
images, menus, animations, and much more.
And managing resources separately from
the application has several benefits,
one of which is that you can
easily alter those resources.
Without having to change or recompile
your application source code in any way.
One common resource type is strings.
In Android,
there are three types of string resources.
Individual strings,
arrays of strings, and plurals.
Now I think strings and a, arrays of
strings are pretty self explanatory.
Let's talk about plurals.
Plurals are basically
string arrays that can be
used to choose specific strings that
are associated with certain quantities.
Such as one book or two books.
And the strings are typically
stored in an XML file in
the res/values directory
of your application.
And the format is, an XML string
tag containing a name attribute and
then containing the actual string itself.
And that actual string can
include formatting and
styling information,
things like HTML tags, for example.
Finally, other resource files
can refer to the strings that
you've defined as ampersand
string/string_name.
In Java code,
you can also access these strings but
this time you do it as
R.string.string_name.
So here we are again in Eclipse.
I've defined some strings for
the map location application.
Let's open these strings.xml file
in the res/values directory.
This file shows two strings.
Show_map_string.
With the value show map and
location_string with
the value Enter Location.
Now I've also defined a second strings.xml
file, this time for the Italian language.
And it's in the res/values-it directory.
And that IT prefix in
the directory name is what
tells Android that this is the string
file for the Italian language.
Now if we look at that file,
we'll see the same two strings show
_map _string, and location_string.
But this time, their values are Italian
words, rather than English words.
In the example I just showed,
if your default language is Italian,
then location string will have the value,
[FOREIGN].
Otherwise, it'll have the value,
enter location.
Let's see that in action.
Now, I'm going to run Map Location twice.
The phone on the left uses English as
its default language while the phone on
the right uses Italian
as its default language.
Now, as you can see, although both phones
are using the same exact source code.
The phone on the left
displays English strings,
while the phone on the right displays
Italian strings.